<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loyall subiect's retiring-roome, opened in a sermon at St Maries, on the 13th day of Iuly, (being Act-Sunday) in the after-noone. A.D. 1645, before the Honourable members of both Houses of Parliament, assembled in Oxford. / By R, H. M, A. [sic].</title>
            <author>Harwood, Richard, d. 1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E300_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861057</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861057</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86088)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E300[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loyall subiect's retiring-roome, opened in a sermon at St Maries, on the 13th day of Iuly, (being Act-Sunday) in the after-noone. A.D. 1645, before the Honourable members of both Houses of Parliament, assembled in Oxford. / By R, H. M, A. [sic].</title>
                  <author>Harwood, Richard, d. 1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversity.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLV. [1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.H. = Richard Harwood.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber 5th" [i.e. September 5th].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXVI, 20-21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113185:1"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
               <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <hi>Outer,</hi> and an <hi>Inner.</hi> The outer, in the <hi>Letter, Chriſtian Prudence.</hi> The inner, in the <hi>Allegory, Christian Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prudence</hi> in a ſeaſonable flight, when a danger threatens. <hi>Enter thou into thy chambers, ſhut the doores about thee &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 27.44.</note> As <hi>Rebecca</hi> commanded <hi>Iacob</hi> to fly to <hi>Haran,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 11.22.</note> till <hi>Fſau's</hi> ſury was aſſwaged: or as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> came not out of doores, till the morning, when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying <hi>Angell</hi> was abroad: So when a <hi>Perſecution</hi> rageth, we muſt nor ſtand to our-face it, but retire into our chambers. This ſenſe <hi>Athanaſius</hi> gives the words, who grounded <hi>his Apology profugá</hi> on the letter of the text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Patience</hi> in a quiet expectation of the Divine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,<note place="margin">A Lapide. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Enter into thy chambers, &amp;c.</hi> Not the <hi>chambers of Death,</hi> Purgatory, <hi>Limbus-patrum,</hi> or the Grave, as the Popiſh Commentators interpret it, of the retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of mortality, till the day of Judgment. Nor the <hi>chambers of pleaſure,</hi> ſuch chambering hath wantoneſſe alwayes behind the Hangings,<note place="margin">Carthuſian B<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Muſe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but <hi>the chambers of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion,</hi> patiently waiting for the ſalvation of the Lord. For if you pleaſe to light one candle by another, this of the <hi>Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luther in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. Cubicula in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredimur, ſuſecreta mer<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> noſtrae in<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licita <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ria<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>us. Greg. <hi>1.4.</hi> mor. <hi>6.26.</hi>
               </note> by that of the <hi>Pſal. Luther</hi> ſales they give the ſame light; <hi>Frett not thy ſelfe, becauſe of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rest in the Lord and waite patiently for him. Pſal.</hi> 77. 7 O if this candle burne too dimme, will you bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Taper of the Fathers? <hi>Cubicula ingredimur,</hi> ſaies Gregory, <hi>we enter into our chambers, when we retire into the ſecret cloſets of our ſoules, we ſhut the doores about us, when we coerce unlawfull deſires;</hi> or as the ordinary gloſſe, <hi>when we put a watch before the doores of our lipps,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113185:1"/>leaſt the greatneſſe of our miſery,<note place="margin">Pone cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ori, ne ex vehememia tribulationis verkaper rumant in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſam dei. Gloſs, ordin.</note> prompt our tongues to blaſphemy and murmuring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly the Argument of both, drawne from
<list>
                  <item>1. The brevity of Affliction, <hi>Paululum ad momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, for a very little moment.</hi> If there be any ods in minutes take the leaſt of them: and that not multiplyed, but <hi>donec pertranſeat ira, till the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be over paſt:</hi> 'Tis a verbe of ſpeed, and bids you look up to the skie, and ſee how faſt this cloude poſts away on the wings of the winde.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſpeedy releife we ſhall have from
<list>
                        <item>1. Heaven. <hi>Ecce venit dominus, behold the Lord commeth. &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. Earth. <hi>Terra revelabit, the earth ſhall reveale her blouds,</hi> and <hi>no longer co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her ſlaine.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the parts of our preſent diſcourſe, and for their multiplicity, I ſhall need no other apology, then that they are like the <hi>ſix cities of refuge,</hi> each a Sanctuary, and I cannot throw open too many in theſe times of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> yet becauſe he that hath many places to viſit, muſt not ſtay long in a place, I ſhall diſcover them to you, with all poſſible brevity, beginning with that which begins all our diſcourſe, the <hi>Complement,</hi> in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>My people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a meere complement you may think it indeed,<note place="margin">1. The Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> that he ſhould call a company of poore captive Iewes, <hi>His people.</hi> He is not a <hi>true Courtier</hi> on earth, that will beſtow more then a Complement on men in miſery. But there is no ſuch baſe Courtſhip in heaven. All God's complements are reall performances: He is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113185:2"/>not aſhamed to owne his people when they are at the worſt. In <hi>captivity,</hi> as well as in <hi>liberty,</hi> the worſt condition: In <hi>Babylon,</hi> as well as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the worſt place. <hi>Populi mei, my people,</hi> in both. Nay when all happineſſe and comfort ſeem to diſclame them, then he invites them to himſelfe, <hi>Come my people.</hi> Come? Lord, they have but a <hi>ſhort ſtep</hi> to thee, who art alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them. When the world was covered with a Sea,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.17.</note> for <hi>fecit inhabitare,</hi> he brought a flood of waters upon the earth, <hi>Ierome</hi> reads it, <hi>Deus inhabitans,</hi> God <hi>dwelt</hi> upon the <hi>deluge.</hi> He would not truſt his <hi>little world</hi> in the <hi>Arke,</hi> but li<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e another <hi>Neptune,</hi> he muſt ſit upon the waters and ſeeme to venture the hazard of a ſhiprack with it. Ere <hi>Iſrael</hi> trode a ſtep towards <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, I will go downe with thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 46.4.</note> ſaith the Lord. <hi>Downe?</hi> what a word is that for a Deity? <hi>into Aegypt?</hi> what a place, that, for his holyneſſe. Yet, <hi>O the humility of our God!</hi> He never thinks himſelfe low enough to doe his people good, no place too had for his ſociety, which made it a rule among the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors,<note place="margin">Menoſ Ben. Iſr. in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>that God and his peole are inſeparable,</hi> he will beare a ſhare in their misfortunes. <hi>Moſes</hi> had the <hi>Hieroglyphick of it,</hi> when he appeared to him in <hi>a burning buſh.</hi> A ſtrange throne for ſuch a majeſtie: yet here he laies aſide the <hi>ſtate of a Deity,</hi> and to reſcue his people from the fire, puts himſelf into the mid'ſt of it. Will you but knock at <hi>Joſephs</hi> priſon doore, and there they will tell you, <hi>Dominus cum illo,<note place="margin">Gen, 39.21.</note> the Lord was with him.</hi> Will you but caſt your eye with <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> into the <hi>Fornace,</hi> and with <hi>Darius</hi> peep into <hi>Daniels denne,</hi> and in both <hi>Angelus Domini, the Angell of the Lord,</hi> put nature to a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113185:2"/>contradiction; you have a fire burning and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming, The devourers devoured by their own prey, <hi>My people are gone into captivity,<note place="margin">Iſai. 52.4, 5.</note> Aſhur hath afflicted them without a cauſe, Et quià mihi nunc hìc,</hi> ſaies the the Lord, <hi>what do I now here?</hi> why, where would'ſt thou be, <hi>O Lord,</hi> but in heaven? is not that the Palace of thy Majeſty? yet he ſeemes to be <hi>at little eaſe</hi> in heaven, whil'ſt his people are in durance on earth: his bondage is their captivity, and there is no heaven to him like his peoples Priſon: or if you will read it otherwiſe (as ſome doe) <hi>Quid mihi nunc, what is now left me?</hi> you will wonder the more, that in the loſſe of a few Jewels, he ſhould eſteem himſelfe Plundered of the whole Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. Yet as <hi>the rights of the Crowne</hi> are all equall, and by ſlipping off one of thoſe flowers, 'tis a ſhrewd figne given all may be lyable: ſo the divine providence hath an even property in all his Saints, and if he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſome to be loſt, he would bring <hi>his originall right</hi> in queſtion. But this hath bin diſputed by a <hi>deluge,</hi> and that could not obliterate; with the <hi>flames,</hi> and they would not conſume; <hi>with age,</hi> and that could not anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate, with all the <hi>powers of darkneſse,</hi> and they could never get it by conqueſt. It hath puzled the whole <hi>Presbytery of hell</hi> to forge a <hi>Smectimuus</hi> againſt this <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re divine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what a bold enemy hath God now upon earth, that dares <hi>out law</hi> whole kingdoms, and daſh a nation at once out of <hi>the book of life,</hi> as if none were <hi>truely Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the King of heaven,</hi> but <hi>the ſtouteſt Rebels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King on earth.</hi> O malice, where are thy bounds? Is it not enough, that thou haſt baniſhed us
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113185:3"/>from <hi>our cities, our country, our houſes,</hi> but wilt thou diſfranchize <hi>us of the new Jeruſalem,</hi> diſinherit <hi>us of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, our trueſt home?</hi> Is it not ſufficient, that thou haſt ſtiptus of our <hi>dearest friends and fortunes,</hi> but wilt thou rob us of <hi>our God too?</hi> Is it no eaſe to thee, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne us <hi>for dead men while we live,</hi> and to make us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to ſerve God and the King, but wilt thou pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue us in our gaves, and perſecute us to the ſentence of an <hi>eternall rume.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I ever eſteemed S.<note place="margin">Ribad. in vit. S. Aug</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the more <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound Doctor,</hi> for being called by the <hi>Manichees Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do anima<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>am</hi> the <hi>Pyrate of ſoules:<note place="margin">Tortus p, 97.</note> King Iames</hi> the founder <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> for being the <hi>Popes Heretike,</hi> &amp; you the more <hi>orthodox Chriſtians,</hi> becauſe you are the <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Papiſts:</hi> yet I pray God our wicked lives have not atticulated this Blaſphemy to them. For will you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem <hi>Him a Roman,</hi> that always walkes in a <hi>Perſian habite, Him</hi> an <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> whoſe language is <hi>pure Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> or <hi>Him</hi> an <hi>Engliſhman;</hi> whom nature hath died a very <hi>Aethiopian?</hi> If we are God's people, <hi>true Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites indeed,</hi> we ſhould weare the habite, ſpeak the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and live according to the Lawes and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Kingdom. When the <hi>Curaſhier Biſhop</hi> was preſented to the <hi>Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Speed Hen. 4.</note> he would not owne him for his Sonne, <hi>Hae non eſt tunica filij, This is not the eoate of my Sonne.</hi> And when God ſhall behold us in our <hi>exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike faſhions,</hi> dreſſed with the vanities of all forraigne Nations, when the times call for <hi>ſack-cloth and aſhes:</hi> when he ſhall heare us ſpeake in that <hi>infernall language</hi> of execrations and blaſphemies, when <hi>bleeding England</hi> begs for our <hi>prayes:</hi> When he ſhall ſee <hi>our faces ſpeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113185:3"/>and pyed,</hi> to court and adulterous eye, when our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miſeries <hi>ſhould bedew them with teares</hi> to pacifie our angry God, what can we except but <hi>a Non novi, I know you not.</hi> This is not the habite, the language, nor complexion of my people: very true in the old law, where we do not read that every <hi>your ſtrang ſpotted beaſts were accepted for ſacrifice.</hi> The claime God layes to us is by right of<note n="a" place="margin">Colof. 1.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>dominion,</hi> and ſo we owe him <hi>ſubjection;</hi> by right of <hi>purchaſe,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.20.</note> ſo <hi>gratitude;</hi> by right of<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>Con queſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Homage;</hi> by<note n="d" place="margin">Exek. 16.8.</note> 
               <hi>Covenant,</hi> ſo <hi>Fidelity:</hi> yea by a ſweer<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>Communion</hi> and ſo we owe him our <hi>deareſt affection.</hi> And cannot all the <hi>cords of love</hi> binde our Allegiance? Into what a <hi>ſacred ſnare</hi> hath the <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> brought himſelf, whereby he is <hi>chain'd up</hi> as it were, and bound to be <hi>Our God,</hi> and yet no <hi>bonds</hi> can hold us to our <hi>Obedience.</hi> Neceſſity hath forced the proudeſt heart to be aſſiſtance of that hand, which proſperity taught him to ſcorne: And me thinks, if there were no other argument left us but <hi>our owne miſery,</hi> it ſhould teach us ſo much wiſdome as to keeepe <hi>God our friend.</hi> The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath long called upon <hi>her lovers,</hi> but ſhe finds them, as her elder Siſter did, <hi>Falſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 1.19</note> 
               <hi>Deceperunt me , they have deceived me.</hi> Humane friendſhip is like <hi>Quick-ſilver,</hi> which you may incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate into <hi>Gold,</hi> but caſt it into the fire, and 'twill <hi>ſteale away,</hi> as if it ſcorn'd it's acquaintance: but the divine love is not made of ſuch <hi>running mettall;</hi> The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an cannot be caſt into <hi>a Furnace of affliction,</hi> that is <hi>too hot for his maker.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>fiery tryall</hi> indeed, but of <hi>God's love,</hi> as well as the <hi>Chriſtian's faith.</hi> As the <hi>King of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon</hi> was ſayling into <hi>Sicily,</hi> he obſerv'd the <hi>brids</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113185:4"/>the ſhip,<note place="margin">Panormitan lib. <hi>1.</hi> derelus geſt. Alphonſi.</note> 
               <hi>whil'ſt he threw corne to them:</hi> but when they had <hi>eaten that up, away they flew,</hi> whereupon ſaies he, <hi>Perſimiles his garriſs purpur all &amp; curiales mei, My Peeres and Courtiers are very like theſe birds;</hi> I ſhall have their company by ſea and land, ſo long as I feed and dignifie them: but if my treaſure fayle, they take their wings, leaving <hi>me and the ſhip</hi> to the mercy of the ſtorme. <hi>Great Alphonſus,</hi> thy Court is but the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me of all mankind: ſo <hi>Scottiſh and coveteo us</hi> are the hearts of men, that there cannot be <hi>a true loves-knott</hi> tyed amongſt them, <hi>but in chaines of gold, and threds of ſilver:</hi> but our God is no <hi>mercenary diety.</hi> He followes not our ſhip for booty or pillage: but as <hi>Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> one ſtyled her ſelf,<note place="margin">Speed, Cron.</note> 
               <hi>the poore man's Queene:</hi> ſo out God is the <hi>Baniſh't, Impriſoned, Plundered, poore mans God. My people?</hi> Lord, whom doſt thou ſpeak to? wilt thou owne us in our bloud, and look upon us in our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery? We have been indeed, <hi>Gens deo chara, A nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved:</hi> but now (O our misfortune!) <hi>Inviſa deo, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr'd of the Almighty.</hi> Once <hi>Rignum Dei, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God:</hi> but now, (O our fall!) <hi>Magnum latroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, A den of Theeves.</hi> May we not ſay with <hi>Rebecca, if it be ſo, why am I thus?</hi> if we are ſtill <hi>thy people, Lord,</hi> why are we <hi>thus efflicted?</hi> But did you never heare, what <hi>Auſonius</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Caeſar,</hi> when he deſir'd a copy of his Verſes,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Aug. Caſ.</note> 
               <hi>Non habed idingenij, I have not ſo good a fancy,</hi> O Emperour: <hi>but command me and I ſhall have, Cur me poRe negern, poRe quodille putat, why ſhould I ſay, I cannot doe, what he thinks I can: So if God ſtill call <hi>us his people,</hi> why ſhould we think we are not? Did he owne us in <hi>our Sinnes,</hi> and will he diſclaime us in <hi>our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113185:4"/>Sorrowes?</hi> could our very <hi>Injuries</hi> move him to compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion, and ſhall our <hi>calamities</hi> enrage him againſt us: Is it his cuſtome to make men miſerable, and then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre them? <hi>If he chaſten every Sonne whom he loves,</hi> adverſity ſure is but an argument of his dearer affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Will any man take the paines to prune a <hi>Vine,</hi> that is none of his owne, or weede the <hi>Garden,</hi> that is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans? Propriety is the ground of care, and by this we know we are <hi>his people, that he careth for us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 34.11.15.</note> When King <hi>Edward</hi> told <hi>John</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> his Priſoner, that he ſhould have his liberty, if he would but doe him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage for the Realme of <hi>France,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">French Hiſt. in <hi>Iohn. 51.</hi> King.</note> He anſwered him free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, like a King, <hi>That he muſt not ſpeak to him of that, which he neither ought, nor would doe, to alienate a right inali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enable: Affliction may engage my perſon, but never the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vielable right of my Crowne.</hi> And doe you think the God of heaven will debaſe himſelfe to doe homage to thoſe two proud uſurpers, <hi>the World and Devill</hi> for his dominions? no, <hi>His Propriety is as in alienable and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mort all as Himſelfe.</hi> Though now our ſhip be almoſt ſinking, yet becauſe it is <hi>his Veſsell,</hi> 'tis an undoubted ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to me, that he will rebuke the tempeſt, and bring it ſafe to land. <hi>Doe you thinke the God of heaven will looſe his right?</hi> Though our Soveraigne be now perſecuted his life and honour, yet becauſe, <hi>He is God's Anoynted,</hi> you may be confident, he will reſtore him to his Crowne and Dignity. <hi>Doe you thinke the God of heaven will looſe his right?</hi> Though the Church ne now almoſt buried in her owne ruines, yet becauſe it is <hi>His houſe,</hi> He will repaire it into it's former Beauty and Luſtre. <hi>Did you ever know the God of heaven cheated</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113185:5"/>of his right?</hi> In a word, where ever we caſt our eyes now, we behold nothing but miſery and deſtruction, yet becauſe he is ſtill pleaſed to owne us as <hi>His peculiar people,</hi> we may aſſure our ſelves, that notwithſtanding our manifold provocations, he will yet looke upon us for good,<note place="margin">Malach 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>and in the day, that he maketh up his fewels, ſparens, as a man ſpareth his owne Sonne. Never thinks the God of heaven will looſe his right:</hi> But that we may ſtill take the boldneſſe to preſent our ſelves before him, <hi>as his owne in Chriſt,</hi> and with the <hi>Preiſt</hi> between the <hi>Porch and the Altar,</hi> make it the argument of our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Iocl. 2.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>ſpare thy people, O God, and give not thy heritage to reproach.</hi> And ſo leaſt you ſhould think I meant to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine you only with a <hi>Complement,</hi> I deſcend to the <hi>Counſell,</hi> my ſecond generall: And therein, Firſt the <hi>Advice of the Letter</hi> Chriſtian Prudence in a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able flight. <hi>Enter thou into thy Chambers, ſhut the doores about thee, and hide thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Chamber was never but ſafe and delightfull to a contemplative mind,<note place="margin">2. The Counſell.</note> but now ſo much the better, as the world is worſe.<note place="margin">1. Literall.</note> 'Tis a happineſſe not to be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the miſcheife of the times, which 'tis as hard to behold, and be innocent, as to converſe with and be ſafe: ſo that he, who needs not <hi>a chamber</hi> for <hi>contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> may for <hi>Protection.</hi> The old law opened <hi>cities of refuge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.23</note> and ſure the Goſpell hath not ſhut them. He that gave the perſecuted counſell, <hi>to fly out of one city into another,</hi> allowes every man the choyce of his owne Sanctuary. When a danger approaches ſo neere, that there is no ſafety in ſtaying, and God offers us the <hi>wings
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113185:5"/>of a Dove,</hi> faire and certaine meanes of eſcape, not to fly then,<note place="margin">Athonaſus Apolog. pro fuga.</note> were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> phraſe, <hi>to condemne providence it ſelfe,</hi> &amp; to ſcorne deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, when 'tis kindly adminiſtred. For though God be omnipotent and can fetch a deliverance for us out of an <hi>Impoſsibility,</hi> yet becauſe his power is commanded by his will, and his will is to ſave by meanes, <hi>Abomni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentiâ Dei non eſt inferendum quidlibet,</hi> We muſt not preſume to inferre more from his omnipotency, then what is authorized by his will: elſe we ſhould make no more uſe of God's imperiall power, then we do <hi>of juglers, only to ſhew tricks to the world, &amp; to pleaſe every man's humour, with a freſh miracle.</hi> Who can read without admiration, that God ſhould fly from a weake man that he <hi>before whom the earth moves, and the ſeas goe backward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoca. 20. v. 11</note> ſhould be put to this poore ſhift to ſave his life from him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.7.</note> whom a <hi>deſpicable worme</hi> could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer: yet our Saviour fled into <hi>Aegypt, leaving us an example that we might follow his ſteps.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. v. 21.</note> He could have commanded an officer of heaven to have ſtroke <hi>Herod</hi> dead, or call'd out a <hi>Legion of Angels</hi> for his life-guard, but that he would inſtruct our preſumption, not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an <hi>Act of grace,</hi> where the <hi>Common-Law</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve us: not to look for a <hi>Miracle,</hi> where <hi>ordinary pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> will protect us. Why doe you not call home your Armies, and diſmount your Ordinance, if you can ortaine the victory by <hi>ſounding of Rams-hornes and breaking of Pitchers,</hi> yet with ſuch an <hi>Artillery, Iſrael</hi> battered <hi>Iericho</hi> to the ground? Nay, why ſo much proviſion for a Seidge, if you can perſwade the heavens
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113185:6"/>to fill your Magazins with <hi>Manna</hi> enough? yet they were ſo curteous to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> campe: but, if you dare not truſt ſuch an <hi>Artillery,</hi> or <hi>Sucklers</hi> to your Army, why will you venture your lives on a certaine danger, upon the preſumption of an extraodinary and diſingaged providence?</p>
            <p>Nor doth it excuſe the raſhneſſe, that <hi>Perſecution is God's viſitation.</hi> For what evill is not? <hi>The ſword of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence,</hi> as well as the <hi>ſword of Warre,</hi> both are weapons of divine juſtice: And why will you court one more then the other? doe you make any difference, whether you periſh by a <hi>ſtab</hi> or by an <hi>infection?</hi> Since then the danger is equall, why not to be declined with equall prudence. <hi>Lot</hi> did not think it ſafe ſtaying among the flames of <hi>Sodome, becauſe they came from heaven:</hi> nor would the people embrace the <hi>Leper,</hi> for the <hi>divine hand</hi> that ſmote him. This were not to periſh <hi>by Gods viſitation,</hi> but <hi>our owne preſumption,</hi> and to <hi>fetch</hi> in a judgment, not to have it <hi>ſent</hi> us; he that bid us fly, when we are perſecuted, did not except himſelfe, when, with reverence be it ſpoken, <hi>he became a Perſecuter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whether can we fly from God's hand? Can we be too nimble for our deſtiny? or cheat the fates by changing our Hemiſphere? No, as <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> told <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> whom he had elected his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour in that <hi>See,</hi> but ſaw him decline it: ſo our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny ſaies,<note place="margin">Ribadin. in vit. Athnaſi.</note> 
               <hi>Fugere licet, Athanaſi, non tamen effugies. Fly thou maiſt, Athanaſius, but thou ſalt not eſcape.</hi> Death is a common debt we owe to nature, yet he is not ſo <hi>cruell a Creditour,</hi> as to demand it before'tis due. The time of payment is ſet downe in God's booke, and ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113185:6"/>long as we have any lawfull meanes to preſerve our lives, the dare is not yet expired.<note place="margin">Ierom. in Ioh.</note> 
               <hi>Nomeſt noſtrum arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere mortem, ſed illatam libentèr accipere:</hi> We muſt <hi>bid death welcome</hi> when he comes, but not <hi>hale him to us, and put the ſit he in his hand whether he willor no:</hi> this were to antidare our owne ruine, and to make death it ſelfe <hi>guilty of murder</hi> by cutting us down before our time. Though <hi>Martyr dome</hi> be the <hi>Crowne of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> yet we may not be ſo ambitious of it, as to betray our ſelves to the Priſon or Stake,<note place="margin">Furioſum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus hominum. Aug. epiſt. ad Bonifac.</note> as thoſe <hi>furious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques,</hi> the Circumcellions in <hi>Auſtines</hi> time, that went up and downe begging Martyr dome, <hi>Come, Plunder, Stab, Burne us; and if none would be ſo kind as to kill them, they were ſo cruell as to become their owne execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners.</hi> The <hi>Fryers</hi> relate of their good Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> that he went up and down to <hi>Majorka,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bonavent. &amp; Ribadin in vitâ Franciſci.</note> and <hi>Minorka,</hi> among the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> deſiring to be put to death for Chriſt's ſake; <hi>pitty, he ſhould goe ſo farre for a halter, that had ſuch a mind to it.</hi> But Chriſt himſelfe was of another opinion, who hearing the <hi>Iewes</hi> had conſulted to deſtroy him,<note place="margin">John. 11.54.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he walked no more openly, but retyred into a Village neare a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> to teach all his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Origen in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taná Pat<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> ſaies, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Not to be too raſh and hot upon dangers, though it be for truth it ſelfe.</hi> A wiſe <hi>Pilot</hi> will not run his ſhip wilfully on a rock, but if a tempeſt drive it, he will ſhew his skill and courage to ſave it from ſplitting. That Commander needs not an enemy, that will drive his men on the Cannons mouth. His temerity ſhall ſlay more then the enemies ſword:or if he chance to <hi>ſlunder
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113185:7"/>upon ſucceſſe,</hi> yet he is more conquered with ſuch a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, then by a diſcomfiture. So, he that ſeeks death, before death ſeeks him, dyes not a <hi>Martyr,</hi> but a <hi>Man. ſlayer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Clem. Alex. l. <hi>4.</hi> Strom.</note> For what difference is there, between falling on my owne and running upon the point of another mans ſword? He that dilivers himſelfe into the hand of danger, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He joynes in conſpiracie with his perſecuter against his owne life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clem. d. l.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if any man ſhould be ſo unkind to his owne ſoule, as to throw it away, yet he <hi>owes ſo much chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to his very perſecuter, as not to give him an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſhed innocent bloud: <hi>As Nazianzen</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves of <hi>Marcus Arethuſius</hi> his flight, that it was not ſo much in love to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Nazlan. orat. <hi>3.</hi> adv. Iuſian.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>but in compaſsion to his perſecuters, least he ſhould fuell their malice with his owne bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Think me not though, ſo faint hearted an Oratour, as to perſwade any man to fly from his Colours. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is no ſuch <hi>cowardly Religion:</hi> but there goe ſo many flowers to make up this crowne of Martyrdom, that he, who doth but <hi>ſimply dye</hi> for Chriſt, without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances, is like to weare but a <hi>ſingle flower,</hi> not the <hi>whole crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Cuipatientia, mens benè conſcia, congruacauſa,</l>
               <l>Tempus &amp; adſuerit, hic benè Martyr erit,</l>
            </q>
            <p>As my Countryman<note n="*" place="margin">Alexander ſir-named of <hi>Hales,</hi> a ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let near <hi>Sude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter ſhire</hi> The only lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writer my Country hath to boaſt of. <hi>Speed.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alexander of Hales</hi> makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a Poſey. <hi>He that hath patience, a good conſcience, a just cauſe,</hi> and (what makes the Crowne compleat) <hi>a fit opportunity</hi> to dye for Chriſt, He only deſerves the name of <hi>a Full Martyr.</hi> The other <hi>three</hi> are like flowers in <hi>Autumne, withered</hi> and <hi>dry,</hi> till God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113185:7"/>time: then they will bloſſome and ſpring, and flouriſh in the <hi>Crowne</hi> ſo that a future threatned danger we may decline without imputation of Cowardize, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Origen. loc: dect.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of the uncertainty of the event:</hi> but a preſent unavoydable one, we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe with the higheſt expreſſion of valour. When our Saviour's <hi>houre was come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.23. Mat. 26.50.</note> he called his <hi>friend Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Devill,</hi> for diſſwading him from his Paſſion, &amp; the <hi>Devill Judas, friend,</hi> for betraying him to it. Wonder not at <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and <hi>Germanicus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ignat: Ep. al Rom. Luſeb. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> Socrates. Scholaſtic. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> et <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> who being both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to the mercyles teeth of wild Beaſts, <hi>provoked</hi> thoſe ſavage creatures to teare them in peices. Cenſure not S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Baſil's Vtinam,</hi> when his immodeſt perſecuter <hi>Modeſtus</hi> threatned him, with preſent death. <hi>Would to God it might goe ſo well with me,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>as to leave this carcaſse of mine in the quarrell of Christ.</hi> Did you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>three Chriſtians</hi> laid on a griditon by <hi>Amachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> to be broyled to death, what could you expect, but teares, and ſupplications for mercy, or an open renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of their faith: yet as if thoſe burning coales had only kindled their zeale, they gave him this flour, <hi>If thou doſt long, O Amachius, after broyled meat, turne the other ſide of us, leaſt thou make but a raw feast of it, and the bloud run about thy teeth.</hi> Such was the undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted courage of the Saints, when they ſaw a neceſſity of ſuffering, that they more tormented the Perſecuter with their conſtancy, then he could them with his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, God knowes, how many of our lots is may be, to drink of this bitter cup: keep in our chambers we may, and pray with our Saviour. <hi>If it be poſsible let this cup paſse from us:</hi> yet if God ſhall put it into any of our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113185:8"/>hand, take it off we muſt with the greateſt cheerfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: 'Tis but a mornings draught, to that long and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py day, <hi>Aeternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tertull I de ſuga in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut. De coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd wilit c. <hi>1.</hi> Thammerus <hi>1.</hi> de ſuga.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Theobaldus Thammerus,</hi> would have the <hi>Preiſt</hi> begin to you in <hi>this cup,</hi> againſt whom they ſhut up all <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> in time of perſecution. The Apoſtles might decline it, if it were offered them <hi>in one city, by flying into another,</hi> becauſe they were <hi>Preachers-gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> Miniſters to the whole world, and ſo whither ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they went, they were ſtill <hi>in their Pariſh,</hi> but we who are Sheepheards to one little flock, if the wolfe come, muſt periſh with them. Forthe <hi>people</hi> are their <hi>owne,</hi> the <hi>miniſter</hi> the <hi>People<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; Them</hi> God hath truſted with their <hi>bodies, Him</hi> with their <hi>ſoules:</hi> Nay, ſhall we preach to them,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.28.</note> 
               <hi>Netimete, Feare not them that kill the body,</hi> and we firſt take our heeles? or did Chriſt ſay it, only to the Laity,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>He that denies me before men, Him will I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny before the Angels of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Specialitèr adverſus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam texuit volumina de pudicitia, de perſecutione, &amp;c. ter. lib. de Eccleſiaſt. ſcriptor. Martyrium aded extolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, us ne fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam, aliaſi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> latebras vel redemptionem vitae admitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Baron. an Chriſti. <hi>201.</hi> n. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> Yet all this is but a kind of <hi>zealous Montaniſme.</hi> For <hi>Tertullian</hi> taking a diſcontent that his countryman <hi>Victor</hi> was preferr'd before him to the <hi>Biſhoprick of Carthage,</hi> after the death of <hi>Agrippinus,</hi> turn'd <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt,</hi> &amp; employed thoſe acute parts of his, in defending many the Hereſies of that Sect, in which catalogue is the <hi>deny all of flight to the perſecuted.</hi> For the <hi>Cataphry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians</hi> ſo magnified Martyrdome; <hi>that they would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a man to ſave his life, though he could without ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall</hi> For my part, I did never love to <hi>uncover the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> of any the <hi>ancient Fathers</hi> of the Church; But when their opinions ſtand in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petition with the truth, then S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath given me a <hi>rule, Non debemus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendre
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113185:8"/>quid aliquis ante nos faciendam putaverit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian. l. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed quid, qui ante omnes, Chriſtus priùs fecerit. We muſt not look what any did before us, but what Chriſt did before all.</hi> He ſcarce ſaluted the world, but declared himſelfe <hi>a man by flight,</hi> as well as by thoſe querulous paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>hunger and thirſt.</hi> And what he did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of men,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſaies,<note place="margin">Athan Apol. pro ſuga.</note> 
               <hi>is common to the whole kind:</hi> And ſhall nature be ſo cruell a Step-mother to our tribe only, as to deny us the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge ſhe indulgeth all her ſonnes? Look into the <hi>Saints Geography,</hi> &amp; you ſhall find a <hi>double Synode,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kin. 18.13.</note> each conſiſting of <hi>fifty Prophets in a cave:</hi> The firſt Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Councell held in <hi>Golgotha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quareſmius Tom. <hi>2.</hi> elucid terrae ſanctae. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grin. <hi>9.</hi> et. c. <hi>22.</hi> peregr. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> among dead mens bones: The Apoſtles had no other <hi>Convocation-houſe, Quareſmius</hi> ſaies, but a <hi>larg cave</hi> or an <hi>ample ſepulchre:</hi> Nor did they like men, but beaſts, <hi>In Latibulis, in their denns and burrowes:</hi> Shall I give you a map of S. <hi>Paul's</hi> flight, out of <hi>his covert</hi> at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Latibulum Pauli fuit an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum in plagâ meridionalt Damaſci, Quareſ. t. d. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> per. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> to <hi>Iconium,</hi> from <hi>Iconium</hi> to <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> from <hi>Lyſtrato Epheſus,</hi> thence to <hi>Macodonia.</hi> You cannot forget old <hi>Polycarpe</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hiſt l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> Ribad. to Vit. S. Aug. Ille in Vit. S. Baſilij. Soz. hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hid in the cockloft,</hi> when his perſecuters ſearch't the houſe for him. S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his chamber, when the people cryed, <hi>Cyprianum ad Leones, Away with him to the Lions.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> lock't within doores, when the <hi>Manichees,</hi> that could not confute him with <hi>argument,</hi> would have done it with the <hi>pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi> S. <hi>Baſil</hi> in the <hi>ſolitude of Pontus,</hi> when the peeviſh Prelate <hi>Euſebius</hi> moleſted him at <hi>Caeſaroa.</hi> And though <hi>Origen</hi> in his youthfull yeares was ſuch a hot ſpurre, as to run upon danger, yet in his riper age and judgement, when <hi>Alexandria</hi> was too hott for him, he was glad to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113185:9"/>accept of <hi>a corner</hi> to ſave his life. What ſhould I tell you of S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ut judices ferat c<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s qui eſſent mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſti hoſtes, Soz <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> who, when there was a Synode pack't by <hi>Theophilus</hi> to condemne him, withdrew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſent them word by <hi>Demetrius, that they must not take him, for Tàm ſlultum, ſo very a fool,</hi> as to be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>ſuch Iudges,</hi> as were his <hi>profeſsed enemies,</hi> but in <hi>a full convention</hi> he would make his defence. Nay <hi>great Athanaſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat Schol. l. <hi>1 6 35</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1, &amp;c.</hi> Ri<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad in l<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it Athan.</note> who for <hi>forty ſix yeares,</hi> was chaſed up and down by thoſe <hi>Arian bloud. hounds, Conſtantine, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius, Julian,</hi> and <hi>Valens,</hi> with ſo much malice and ſeverity, that ſcarce any of the foure Elements did dare protect him, but he was compelled to live in a <hi>Ciſterne,</hi> and ſometimes in his <hi>Fathers toomb</hi> like a dead man.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot paſſe by, <hi>that falſe imputation,</hi> which <hi>Thammerus</hi> caſts on this reonowned Prelate,<note place="margin">Thammerus de fug. l. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> viz. <hi>That the occaſion of his flight, was his own Avarice, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſsing the corne, Conſtantine ſent to the poore of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria:</hi> A foule crime in a Biſhop,<note place="margin">Socrates. l <hi>2</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 19 ad <hi>28</hi> Niceph. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. 9. Theod. biſs. Eccleſ. l 2, c <hi>7, 8.</hi> &amp;c. Lib <hi>1</hi> d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>c. <hi>25.</hi> ad <hi>32.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> l <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>35</hi>
               </note> to rob the poore: but of this, and other falſe accuſations preferr'd againſt him by the <hi>Arians,</hi> he was <hi>acquitted before the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> and in a <hi>Councell at Sardica,</hi> a city in <hi>Illyria;</hi> when <hi>Julius Biſhiop of Rome</hi> ſent a ſharp Epiſtle to the <hi>Biſhops of Antioch,</hi> for endeavouring to ſtain ſo <hi>Spotleſse an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence:</hi> the <hi>true cauſe</hi> of his flight being the <hi>bloudy malice</hi> of the <hi>Arian</hi> faction againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fugiant cum corum quiſquam. ſpecia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutori<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us queritur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Aug Ep. <hi>180.</hi> ad Honorat.</note> And truely where the <hi>life</hi> or <hi>liberty</hi> of a Miniſter is ſought (as at this day) I am to learne what obligation ſhould ſtay him for ruine. For he is not ſo much the peoples, but he is ſtill Lord of his owne life: Nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath the care of <hi>their ſoules,</hi> is it any warrant, he ſhould neglect his <hi>owne.</hi> Our <hi>charity</hi> may <hi>begin</hi> at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113185:9"/>our ſelves, though I would not have it <hi>end there.</hi> If my my <hi>conſcience</hi> tells me, I ſhall not be able to conteſt with the temptation, that I have not <hi>patience for apri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; nor courage for a ſtake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. a. v. 13.</note> Then as the Angell ſaid to <hi>Ioſeph, Ariſe</hi> I muſt, and take the young Childe, <hi>My weak faith,</hi> and fly into <hi>Aegytt.</hi> Better a prudent flight, then a preſumptuous reſidence. I had rather accept of S. <hi>Paul's basket at Damaſeus,</hi> and keep my faith,<note place="margin">Act, 9 25.</note> then fit by the <hi>high Preiſts fire</hi> with <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 691</note> and deny my Maſter:<note place="margin">Pet. Mart. Ep ad Lucenſ. Euſeb. l. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> With <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> rather leave my Church at <hi>Luca</hi> &amp; enjoy a good conſcience: then keep my Living and looſe my faith with <hi>Quintus.</hi> Sure he cannot be faid to <hi>deny</hi> Chriſt by <hi>flying,</hi> who <hi>flyes leaſt,</hi> he ſhould <hi>deny him.</hi> Nay what more reall, and publique <hi>confeſsion</hi> can he make of his faith, then to leave all for his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? Lock upon his plunder'd houſe, his ſcatter'd pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, nay the poor man's cheeks, that were fed with his bread, and doe they nor all ſuffer a <hi>kind of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> for his Allegiance? Can you behold his Wife and Children, the conſtant addition, and companions of his misfortunes, and doe they not all ſee me to you <hi>ſo many confeſſours</hi> of his Loyalty? Nay where another <hi>Curate</hi> can't be had, what if I ſhould ſay, <hi>Domus ipſa di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinat,</hi> The <hi>very Parſonage houſe,</hi> can Preach <hi>obedience</hi> to the whole Pariſh? Tell me now, which <hi>denyes Chriſt before men,</hi> He that ſits ſecure at home, and <hi>Rebels,</hi> or He, that expoſeth himſelfe to all difficulties, to keepe a good conſcience. He that ſtayes in his houſe, and goes to <hi>Maſse,</hi> or He, that flyes to keep himſelfe from <hi>Idolls. Peter Martyr</hi> upbraydes the preſumption of his <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners,</hi> who eſteemed him a <hi>Coward</hi> for his prudence,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113185:10"/>and boaſted that they were <hi>Equites Chriſti fortes &amp; probati Valiant and approved Cavaleirs of Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet Mart Ep. <hi>2.</hi> ad fra: Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens. p. <hi>1104.</hi>
               </note> that would rather dye, then ſtirre a foot from. <hi>Chriſt's Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and yet ranne to the enemy, and faught under a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Enſigne. O quàm multos fefellit haec vana ſpes? How many hath this vaine hope deceived?</hi> whil'ſt they deſpiſe this <hi>common remedy of weakneſse,</hi> or rather <hi>true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an policy,</hi> they run their conſciences on a wilfull, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ruine.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Miniſters <hi>abſence vncharitable,</hi> where his <hi>preſence is vnprofitable:</hi> For it is not <hi>his abſence,</hi> but the <hi>peoples profeſsion,</hi> that expoſeth them to the Wolfe: not <hi>his flight,</hi> but <hi>their faith,</hi> that invites the perſecuter. Or if he did ſtay, when his office ceaſeth, He is <hi>ſpiritually abſent</hi> (the worſt of the two) though corporally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: yea, how unable were he to confirme the <hi>weake,</hi> who himſelf is the <hi>weakeſt?</hi> ſo that, where the people can have no benefit of his preſence, they are his greateſt Perſecuters, that quarrell with his abſence. Will you not allow him to learne to handle his weapon in a chamber, that he may come prepared, and not be hiſſed off the ſtage?<note place="margin">Athan. Apol. pro fugd.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Flight is a fencing Schoole,</hi> where we exerciſe our ſelves at <hi>foyles with death,</hi> ere we come to <hi>a publique encounter.</hi> Call it no more <hi>Feare</hi> that he is gone, but <hi>Art:</hi> not <hi>cowardize,</hi> but <hi>ſtrategem.</hi> He is ſtept aſide, as the <hi>Fencer</hi> falls back ſometime, to give the feircer onſet: or the <hi>Souldier</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats, only to returne with greater courage to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. Have you but the patience, till the cloud breaks, and the Sunne will recompence your ſhort darkneſſe with a more glorious light. Chriſt ſhall ſtay no longer in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113185:10"/>then till <hi>Herod</hi> is dead: <hi>then,</hi> the Sunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall riſe in <hi>Inry</hi> with <hi>heading in his wings.</hi> Let not <hi>Carthage</hi> thinke they have quite loſt their <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. Ep. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> in leſſe then two yeares <hi>Decius dieth,</hi> &amp; he returns their vigilant <hi>Biſhop and Paſtour.</hi> Doth <hi>Alexandria</hi> deſpaire of ever ſeeing <hi>Athanaſins</hi> againe? why, the very ſame power, that firſt baniſhed, reſtores him againe to his <hi>ſeized Biſhoprick.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. l, <hi>1,</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> For <hi>Conſtantius</hi> is now ſending his <hi>Imperiall letters,</hi> to invite him home, and <hi>devout, George the ſequeſtratour,</hi> muſt out of his uſurped Prelacy. Doe but permit <hi>Luther</hi> to keep cloſe,<note place="margin">Sleid. Anno <hi>1521.</hi>
               </note> till the <hi>Popes Bull hath done roaring,</hi> and you ſhall heare him again in <hi>his pulpit at Witenberge.</hi> Suffer <hi>Melancton</hi> to hide a while in the Cities of <hi>Harcinia:</hi> when the Seidge is raiſed,<note place="margin">Sleid: <hi>1547.</hi>
               </note> he will returne to his <hi>Divinity ſchoole</hi> in that Vniverſity. The text allowes not of <hi>ſuch chamber,</hi> as ſhould entertaine you in a perpetuall ſecurity, but by the <hi>ſeptuagints word,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they are like the <hi>Cabinet,</hi> where you put up your <hi>Iewels</hi> ſafe, till you pleaſe to weare them, or the <hi>common Magazins,</hi> where you lay in proviſion, till ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity calls it forth.</p>
            <p>Beſides, will you make the Almighty ſo <hi>vnskilfull a Generall,</hi> as to venture all his <hi>Army</hi> on the very <hi>first charge:</hi> ſome <hi>Reſerves</hi> he will have for the Neceſſities of his Church: As <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> when one upbrayded his flight, anſwered, <hi>Serve me patrioe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plat.</note> 
               <hi>I keepe my ſelfe for my Country:</hi> ſo the <hi>learned Clergy,</hi> that take fanctuary here, and in other places of ſafety, are but the <hi>Churches Reſerve,</hi> not to be commanded up, till the very laſt plunge of the Battaile. And how many <hi>triumphs</hi> doth the Church owe to this one <hi>Perſecuted Brigade?</hi> When
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113185:11"/>all the <hi>world</hi> was <hi>Arian<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Atha<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſ <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ad orthedox: frat.</note> ſtout <hi>Athanaſius</hi> lead up the <hi>Reſerve</hi> of <hi>Orthodox Biſhops,</hi> and quite <hi>rouſed</hi> the <hi>Here ſie,</hi> that it could never gather a head ſince. When the <hi>Pope</hi> had the <hi>necks</hi> of all <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> under his club foot, and they held their Conſciences, and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Vaſſalagae</hi> from him, did not that poore Reſerve, <hi>Lather a ſingle Monk</hi> cut off this <hi>Philiſtin's</hi> head with his <hi>Owne Sword?</hi> I cannot tell what we ſhould have done for a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> had not <hi>David</hi> ſaved his life in a <hi>Cave</hi> Could you have had the <hi>branch,</hi> if the <hi>ſtocke of Ieſse</hi> had been cut down and withered? Nay we had all been <hi>Pagans</hi> till this day,<note place="margin">Baronius t. <hi>1.</hi> annal.</note> had not ſome of thoſe <hi>fifteent thouſand,</hi> that fled from <hi>feruſalem</hi> at the Stoning of <hi>Steeven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8. 1.</note> croſſed the <hi>Brittiſh ſeas:</hi> By this, the <hi>Romane Scepter</hi> was prevented by the <hi>Croſse of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> made one of the <hi>firſt Chambers,</hi> where <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> was borne. In all the rety rements of theſe <hi>worthies,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> hath reaped a very <hi>plentifull harveſt.</hi> Had ſhoe nor many of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal,</hi> 3. In the Cave, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 57. In the Wilderneſſe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 63. His prayer in the Cave, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 142. <hi>Euſeb</hi> l. 3. c. 15.</note> 
               <hi>David's Pſalme,</hi> out of a <hi>Wilderneſse,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Cave?</hi> choyce flowers, for ſo barren a ſoyle. Saint <hi>Ihon's Revelations,</hi> out of the <hi>Ile Patmos,</hi> the place of his baniſhment: The <hi>Apoſtles Greed,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Oblonga ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterna in rupe montia exciſa <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Quareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius, tom. 2. elucid. terra ſanctae. l. 4. c. 1. pereg 9.</note> out of a <hi>long vault at the foot of mount Olivet</hi>: where the <hi>Twelve</hi> drew it up, ere they diſperſed themſelves throughout the world: The <hi>Athanaſian</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Nauclerus vol. <hi>2.</hi> Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nol generat. <hi>12.</hi> p. <hi>608.</hi> Ribad in Vit. eypr.</note> out of an <hi>old ciſterne</hi> at <hi>Treveris in Germany,</hi> where that Father penn'd it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Arians.</hi> Godly and learned men are of ſuch <hi>a diffuſivanature,</hi> that like the <hi>rivers,</hi> if they be denyed paſſage in their <hi>proper channelts,</hi> they ſwell above the banks, and water the ſterill country about it. S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> being baniſhed <hi>Carthage,</hi> retyred to <hi>Curhis,</hi> confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113185:11"/>the Martyrs, and releiving the poore. S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> in his exile to <hi>Cucuſus</hi> wrote that divine Paradox, <hi>Nemo Laeditur, niſi à ſeipſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi> Ribab. in Vit. Chryſom.</note> and though he found the People <hi>Pagan,</hi> yet he leſt them <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> For by his unwearied paines and exemplary piety, he planted a <hi>Chriſtian Chruch,</hi> and at his departure, ordeined <hi>ſeven Biſhops, and many Presbytens</hi> there. You would think, Ivpbraided your <hi>Idleneſse,</hi> ſhould I tell you of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen's</hi> preaching at <hi>Caeſanea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſm in Vit. Origen Pet Mart. ad Lucenſ. Sleid. l. <hi>3.</hi> an. <hi>1521.</hi> extant tom. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> when he was driven from <hi>Alexandria:</hi> Of <hi>Peten Martyr's.</hi> Divinity Lectures at <hi>Argentoratum,</hi> When he could Preach no longer at <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce:</hi> of <hi>Lather's</hi> tomes, which he wrote in the Caſtle of <hi>Wartenburg,</hi> when they laid wait for his life at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia:</hi> and of <hi>Brentius</hi> his <hi>Commentaries</hi> in his receſſe,<note place="margin">Sleid. k <hi>20.</hi> an <hi>1548.</hi>
               </note> when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> expolled him his Church at <hi>Hala.</hi> You are not of this <hi>reſerve,</hi> whom your Pariſhes have <hi>ſpued</hi> out for your <hi>drunkenneſse</hi> and <hi>luxury:</hi> Nor any, that come hither, as to a <hi>Garden of pleaſures,</hi> to live at eaſe, or as to a <hi>Faire of preferments,</hi> to ger honour and advancement, as too many follow our Aimies, onely <hi>for Quarter and pillage,</hi> who never meane to <hi>draw a ſword.</hi> None are of the <hi>Churches Regiment,</hi> but thoſe whom <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> have brought to this place, and are willing, when God ſhall call, <hi>to lay downe their lives</hi> for the Churches good. As oft as I think of <hi>Witenberg,</hi> I eſteeme every ſuch <hi>Champion</hi> (How meane ſoever he ſeeme to the eye of the World) a <hi>Pledge of divine protection.</hi> For when <hi>Charles the ſift</hi> beſiedged <hi>that Vniverſity,</hi> God ſo heard the prayers of <hi>Pomeranus</hi> and <hi>other learned men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sleid l. <hi>19.</hi> Wig de Jugd miniſte.</note> that, when the <hi>Souldiens</hi> entred, inſtead of <hi>Violence,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113185:12"/>they ſhew'd them all <hi>reverence,</hi> and ſpared the City for <hi>their ſakes.</hi> Pray God, <hi>We</hi> never meet with a <hi>worſe enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the <hi>divine Indulgence,</hi> we have this <hi>Zoar,</hi> this <hi>Pella</hi> yet left us: but if he hath purpoſed, this ſhall not be the <hi>laſt ſtage</hi> of our <hi>ſlight,</hi> as the <hi>Poet</hi> of himſelſe and his friend,<note place="margin">Martial. E. pigr.</note> 
               <hi>Quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, in loce, Roma duobus erit:</hi> ſo, let this be our comfort, that <hi>God</hi> and a <hi>Christian,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are, make a <hi>great city.</hi> He cannot want the conveniences of one place, who is accompanied with him that fills all places, and we may beſure of <hi>His ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> who flye for <hi>his ſake,</hi> as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſaid of <hi>A. thanaſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nor. orat. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He ſled <hi>for the Trinity,</hi> and therefore <hi>with the Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aske me not, <hi>What you ſhall cate, or what you ſhall drinke, or where withall you ſhall be clothed?</hi> Rather then your <hi>Heavenly Father</hi> will ſuffer you to <hi>want any of theſe,</hi> The <hi>Heavens</hi> ſhall raine <hi>Manna,</hi> the <hi>Rocks</hi> run with a <hi>pleaſant ſtreame,</hi> and the <hi>winds</hi> ſerve in <hi>Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties</hi> for you. You have forgot the <hi>Dry cruſe,</hi> that ſprang with oyle, the <hi>Lion's jawes,</hi> that diſtill'd hony, the <hi>Raven,</hi> that carried meat in his bill, and the <hi>Fiſh,</hi> that brought mony in his mouth, to <hi>defray the charges</hi> of God's people. All the creatures are ready to bring in <hi>Contribution,</hi> either <hi>proviſion</hi> or <hi>mony</hi> for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. We cannot ſure be driven into a more barren ſoyle,<note place="margin">Pſ, 63. v. 6.</note> then the <hi>wilderneſse of Ziph;</hi> yet there <hi>David</hi> was <hi>ſatisfied, as with marrow and fatnes.</hi> Doe you not think the <hi>Angell</hi> miſtaken,<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> that he ſhould ſend <hi>foſeph with our Saviour</hi> into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> A <hi>Nation alwayes abhorred of the Iewes:</hi> this were, in your judgement, to deliver
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113185:12"/>him out of one danger into another: yet <hi>there</hi> the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence deſigned him a <hi>ſafe quarter,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided our tender Jeſus a <hi>bed in Heliopolis,</hi> for his <hi>hard manger in Bet blehem.</hi> Whether could you imagine S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Chryſostome</hi> was going, but as a <hi>certaine prey to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> and <hi>miſery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zor. l. d. Ribad. in vit.</note> when he went in baniſhment into <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia,</hi> without <hi>friend or fortune?</hi> yet there God raiſed him two noble friends, <hi>Philadelphus,</hi> and <hi>Dieſcorus,</hi> who eſteemed themſelves happy in ſo <hi>rich a prize,</hi> and became not only <hi>Patrons to his Perſon,</hi> but <hi>Proſelytes to his Religion.</hi> How was it poſſible, <hi>great Athanaſius</hi> could live <hi>ſix yeares in a ciſterne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naucler. vol. <hi>2.</hi> chronol. gen. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>ſoure moneths in his Father's monument,</hi> had not God moved the heart of a <hi>Vertuous matron</hi> to conveigh him dayly reliefe? Will you behold you owne misfortunes in <hi>reverend Brentius,</hi> who after <hi>twenty ſix yeares</hi> conſtant preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Hala in Swethland,</hi> with his Wiſe and Children was, by the bloudy <hi>Papists,</hi> throwne out of his owne <hi>houſe</hi> into a <hi>hoſpitall,</hi> and,<note place="margin">Sleid. l. <hi>20.</hi> an. <hi>1548.</hi>
               </note> as if that had been too ſtately a Pallace for a poore Proteſtant, ſent a begging, had not <hi>Vlrichus</hi> Duke of <hi>Witenberg, Hoſpitium occultum,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him privately in his owne Court. What ſhould I tell you of poore <hi>Merlin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fr. Hiſt.</note> who during the <hi>maſsacre at Paris</hi> (a fortnight together) was fed with <hi>one egge a day,</hi> which a <hi>Hen</hi> layd in the <hi>Hey-mow,</hi> where he hid himſelfe? or of diſtreſſed <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Mart ep. adfr. Lucenſ.</note> whom <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> relieved at his owne Table, till he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd him to be <hi>Divinity reader</hi> at <hi>Argentoratum,</hi> and procured him an honourable ſtipend of the <hi>Senate</hi> Since the divine providence hath found out ſo many <hi>unexpected wayes</hi> of relieving his people, why ſhould
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113185:13"/>we think his hand will be <hi>ſhortned</hi> towards any of us, who are now under the like perſecution? In the Civill Warres of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fran Hiſt.</note> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſcoffed the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that they had neither <hi>Men</hi> nor <hi>mony,</hi> but <hi>a God for all purpoſes,</hi> and this Magazine never failed them. We have almoſt for got <hi>our meane beginning:</hi> who it was, that advanced us out of the duſt to be a terrour to our enemies? Had our King any <hi>Arſenall of Armes,</hi> but <hi>the divine providence?</hi> any <hi>Magazine</hi> left him, but <hi>his God?</hi> doe but continue your affiance in Him, and he will be Riches, honours, friends, maintenance, <hi>All</hi> to you. Or, put the worſt that can be, if our Enemies ſhould bear us off <hi>God's earth,</hi> yet they will but drive us <hi>into Heaven:</hi> and poore prize, they will have of <hi>our bones,</hi> (but a <hi>laſting monument of their owne ſhame</hi>) when our immortall Soules ſhall mount above the Stanes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Clem Alex. l. ſhrow. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> a <hi>Place above the reach of a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> As <hi>Luther</hi> anſwered <hi>Cajetan's</hi> Oratous, when he asked him,<note place="margin">Melanſton in preſat ad town <hi>2.</hi> Lutheri.</note> 
               <hi>where he could live ſafe, if Prince Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick did not protect him,</hi> Siſb Coelo, <hi>Vuder the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſomewhere,</hi> bur if <hi>Earth</hi> will not entertaine me, <hi>Heaven</hi> ſhall, <hi>In my Father's houſe are many manſions,</hi> which puts me in mind of our Inner chamber, <hi>The Allegory,</hi> in <hi>Chriſtian Patience. Enter thou into thy chambers,</hi> &amp;c. This, as well as the Other, my next particular.</p>
            <p>But we have been ſo long in the other,<note place="margin">The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, 2. Allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</note> that as <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, De patieptia dicturus, patiention veſtram, Before I diſcourſe of Patiences I had need be ſeech your patience:</hi> yet as <hi>Moſes</hi> from mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> Had onely a <hi>view of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> a farre off, and <hi>then dyed:</hi> ſo, Pleaſe you onely
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113185:13"/>to <hi>look</hi> into this <hi>Inner roome,</hi> and I ſhall conclude.</p>
            <p>Patience is a <hi>retiring Virtue:</hi> ſhee alwayes keeps her chamber, and never goes abroad to <hi>meet affliction,</hi> but <hi>bids</hi> it <hi>welcome,</hi> when it comes. He is too delicate for her acquaintance, that cannot entertaine ſo <hi>chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a gueſt. Erras, erras frater,</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Ierome</hi> to <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,<note place="margin">Ier, Ep. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liodor.</note> You are miſtaken Brother, you are miſtaken, if you think to be a Chriſtian and not to ſuffer.</hi> Twas <hi>Iulian</hi>'s ſcoffe, but a true one, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>'Tis your duty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Soen.</hi> 1.3.6.12.</note> 
               <hi>when Inſuries are offered you, to beare them patiently.</hi> And if our duty, why are we ſuch <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to this <hi>noble virtue?</hi> Sure you are not ſo <hi>ſtraitned</hi> in <hi>roome,</hi> but that you may ſpare <hi>Patience</hi> a <hi>chamber.</hi> Shee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects not any <hi>ſtately palace,</hi> but a <hi>Quiet mind:</hi> the <hi>leaſt cloſet</hi> you have will ſerve her turne, <hi>But your Hearts.</hi> A cheap gueſt ſhe is: you may ſave your <hi>hangings</hi> and <hi>Perfumes,</hi> ſhe delights in no <hi>Ornaments,</hi> but the <hi>Croſſe:</hi> no <hi>delicacies,</hi> but <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>hope:</hi> ſhee keeps not her chamber for <hi>ſtate,</hi> but <hi>devotion,</hi> and ſhuts the doores againſt all <hi>company,</hi> but <hi>afflictions.</hi> A ſtrange humour this! Can ſhe dwell with miſery and not the deſtroyed with it? Why not? Doe you not ſee the <hi>Keeper</hi> ſport with his <hi>Lion,</hi> when the <hi>Spectatour</hi> will ſcarce truſt <hi>his chaine. Miſery</hi> lookes <hi>terrible</hi> onely upon <hi>ſtrangers.</hi> Let patience bring you acquainted, and though it look <hi>grim</hi> vpon you at firſt, yet you will find it a very <hi>ſweet companion.</hi> For <hi>Patience</hi> can tell thee, All thy miſery is fetcht in by thy ſelfe, or ſent from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If by thy ſelfe,</hi> No greater argument for patience. He that could never forgive another, will not ſure be ſo unkind to himſelfe, this were to adde <hi>Impatience</hi> to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113185:14"/>
               <hi>Imprudence,</hi> and by the ſame reaſon thou vexeſt at thy former errour, thou mayeſt <hi>vex at thy vexing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If from God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. l. de patient.</note> Cui magis patientiam, quam domino? <hi>To whom is our Patience more due, then to the Lord?</hi> He hath borne with our Injuties, and ſhall not we endure his chaſtiſements? <hi>Proud clay,</hi> will thou ever be check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Potter? Inſolent earth,</hi> would'ſt thou controll, where thou ſhouldeſt admire? Is his <hi>Wiſedome</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Himſelfe</hi> infinite, and ſhall not be know what is moſt expedient for thee? Is his <hi>Juſtice</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Himſelfe</hi> mercifull, and becauſe his proceedings ſeeme <hi>harſh,</hi> wilt thou call them <hi>unjuſt?</hi> In fine, Is his <hi>will</hi> the <hi>rule</hi> of his <hi>actions, His goodneſse</hi> of his <hi>will?</hi> And can any thing, <hi>but what is good,</hi> proceed from <hi>goodneſse</hi> it ſelfe?<note place="margin">Cul dew dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur iraſci Tert I.de.pat.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> is in the right, <hi>Beatum illum ſervum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Happy the man, with whom God vouchſafes to be angry!</hi> Suffer him, O ſuffer him to ſcourge thee here, that he may ſpare thee hereafter. For did <hi>Mercy</hi> open all her <hi>bowells</hi> upon thee, yet ſhe could not produce <hi>ſuch another mercy,</hi> as this <hi>very Anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed for a man to be throwne out of <hi>plenty</hi> into <hi>want,</hi> out of a <hi>large Revenue,</hi> unto <hi>almoſt an Almes,</hi> is as <hi>great</hi> a <hi>temptation,</hi> as now <hi>common.</hi> Yet remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, The greater the evill; The more glorious the conqueſt. 'Tis <hi>no Victory,</hi> to vanquiſh a poor worme, <hi>No praiſe,</hi> to wade over a ſhallow <hi>foard;</hi> but to cut the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and encounter a potent Enemy is the <hi>true gallantry,</hi> that deſerves the laurell. <hi>Great evills have this benefit</hi> with them, that their <hi>difficulties</hi> are not ſo <hi>large,</hi> but their <hi>Crownes</hi> are <hi>proportionable,</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113185:14"/>though they require <hi>much patience</hi> to conquer them, yet that is, onely that they may <hi>Crowne</hi> the <hi>Victor</hi> with the <hi>greater glory.</hi> Many of us, I know, were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in <hi>the liſt before;</hi> now we are ſet upon by a <hi>fierce Judgement,</hi> ſhew <hi>what patience</hi> you have, <hi>what forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi> Let not the <hi>Heathen Philoſopher</hi> ſhame you, who could laugh at his <hi>owne ſhipwracke,</hi> when we <hi>cry out,</hi> as if our <hi>eternall happineſse</hi> were embarqued in a <hi>Coffer.</hi> He could throw that <hi>careleſſe Epitaph</hi> after his goods, <hi>Pereant, ne Peream, Let them periſh, leaſt I periſh with them;</hi> but we wiſh, we had ſunke in the ſame bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, or with the diſcontented <hi>Iſraelites, That we had dyed, ere we came out of AEgypt.</hi> What meanes this Impatience, this cowardize? Have the Enemy <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> your <hi>hearts,</hi> as well as your <hi>Lands?</hi> Have they plundered you of your <hi>Faith</hi> together with your <hi>Goods?</hi> me thinks I heare you talke like <hi>Laban, Wherefore have they taken away my Gods?</hi> As if you knew not, what to doe for a <hi>God,</hi> a <hi>Chriſt, a Heaven,</hi> now your <hi>wealth</hi> is gone. Come, diſſemble no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but profeſſe thy ſelfe an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> who knoweſt <hi>no Diety,</hi> but thy <hi>Mammon:</hi> Be no more a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who can'ſt not ſuffer <hi>for righteouſneſse ſake.</hi> Never was any man <hi>looſer</hi> by a <hi>ſjuſt cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Totum ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pereat, modò patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam lucri <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>am, Text. de pat.</note> though he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left him, but <hi>his patience. He is richer with this then with the whole Indies.</hi> Righteouſneſſe will not be long in his debt: but he that hath loſt a <hi>friend</hi> for <hi>Her ſhe</hi> will <hi>pay</hi> him with a <hi>God.</hi> He that is deprived of his <hi>liberty</hi> for <hi>her,</hi> ſhe will <hi>recompenſe</hi> him with a <hi>Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> He that ſhall looſe <hi>Lands,</hi> or <hi>Houſes,</hi> or <hi>Life</hi> for <hi>Hes,</hi> ſhe will repay him with a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> a <hi>Crowne,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113185:15"/>yea <hi>Aeternity</hi> it ſelfe. <hi>O let me ever be ſuch a looſer, and Impatience it ſelfe cannot complaine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, <hi>let not your Hearts be troubled,</hi> but <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſse your Soules in patience.</hi> Non Villas,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> non Laudes, <hi>Not your Farmes, not your Lordſhips,</hi> thoſe you are leaſt maſters of now:but <hi>Animas, Your Soules, That manour</hi> you have ſtill left you: nothing can <hi>diſpoſseſse</hi> you of it, but your <hi>Impatience.</hi> And why will you make a <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi> evill <hi>domeſticall,</hi> and fetch in <hi>thoſe furies,</hi> that are now abroad, <hi>to diſquiet patience in her chamber?</hi> When <hi>Luther</hi> ſaw <hi>Melancton</hi> torne in himſelfe at the diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Church,<note place="margin">Sleid. l. <hi>7.</hi> an. <hi>1330.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cur ad hunc modumte crucias,</hi> &amp;c. ſaid he, <hi>Why doſt thou thus torment thy ſelfe with impatient thoughts? If our Cauſe be naught, why doe we not throw it up? If Just, why ſhould we make God a lyar in ſo many promiſes of ſucceſse?</hi> If ever a <hi>ſad Melanction</hi> be in this Aſſembly, let him intreat his <hi>patience</hi> to keep her chamber but a <hi>moment,</hi> and he, <hi>that is to come, will come and will not tarry:</hi> which is the laſt particular, I ſhall at this time treat of, the <hi>Firſt argument,</hi> which like a <hi>key</hi> locks both chamber doores, <hi>Vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, for a very little moment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are there any minutes in <hi>God's Ephemerides?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Argument, 1. <hi>from the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of our affliction.</hi>
               </note> doe ſuch <hi>atomes of time</hi> come under his <hi>obſervation?</hi> Our <hi>Philomathiſts</hi> have kept their account ſo well, that they have <hi>loſt us</hi> ſome part of our yeare: but God numbers the <hi>dayes,</hi> the <hi>houres,</hi> yea the <hi>very minutes</hi> of our affliction. No ſo <hi>exact a Chronologer,</hi> as the <hi>divine providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet you may ſay unto me, as the Diſciples to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Joh. 16. v. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Quid est hoc modicum, What is this little while?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113185:15"/>we know not what he meaneth.</hi> For the <hi>Jewes</hi> were <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty yeares</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and yet he calls it, <hi>Tanquam param momenti, Not a full minute.</hi> Nay, <hi>Our foure yeares Troubles,</hi> which have ſeemed almoſt <hi>an Age</hi> to us, will he eſteeme, but a <hi>moment!</hi> ô longum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum!<note place="margin">O modicum longum, pledomine, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum eſt &amp; multum val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ninis, <hi>Bern. 74. Ser. in Cant.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>theſe are long minutes indeed,</hi> when ſhall we ſee an end of our ſorrowes? But the Almighty mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures time by <hi>another dyall</hi> then we doe: Not the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sunne,</hi> but the <hi>purpoſe of his will.</hi> The <hi>clocke</hi> was ſet from all eternity, but the <hi>flye</hi> cannot denore the <hi>minutes</hi> and faſter then the <hi>poize, The divine pleaſure,</hi> drives it. Did we ſet our wills by his will, <hi>God's clocke,</hi> and <hi>ours</hi> would alwayes <hi>agree</hi> and <hi>ſtrike deliverance together.</hi> There was a <hi>Diall</hi> in <hi>Campus Martius</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> that never went according to the Sun: And if Our moments, and God's differ, 'tis becauſe they are not ſet by his will. Our deſires are poized with the heavy weights of <hi>ſelfe love,</hi> and <hi>our private ends,</hi> and therefore move faſter, then God's will: ſo that the divine aſſiſtance may happily come <hi>too late</hi> in reſpect of our <hi>Haſty deſires,</hi> but never in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our <hi>True neceſsity.</hi> The ſhorteſt ſtay ſeemes long to a running mind, the longeſt ſhort to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
            <p>Eſteeme not God then <hi>ſlow,</hi> who keepes the <hi>very minute of his promiſe,</hi> though he come not at the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy expectation.</hi> In <hi>Chronicall diſeaſes</hi> you muſt be ruled by your <hi>Phyſitian:</hi> though you may deſire <hi>Phyſicke</hi> in the <hi>Paroxiſme</hi> or <hi>hot ſit,</hi> yet he may thinke it time enough when <hi>the ſit is over.</hi> ſo, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeed</hi> to this ſame <hi>God's-ſpeed,</hi> and then we are to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113185:16"/>judge our <hi>deliverance quick enough,</hi> when he ſhall eſteeme it <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, I have ſeene the <hi>twelve ſignes</hi> of the <hi>Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke</hi> compaſſe a <hi>Dyall,</hi> and denote the <hi>twelve houres</hi> of the days <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>ſignes</hi> about his <hi>Watch</hi> too, <hi>Faith, Repentance,</hi> &amp;c. but <hi>Deliverance</hi> is one of the <hi>last:</hi> now would you have the clocke ſtrike <hi>Twelve before One, deliverance before repentance?</hi> this is againſt the <hi>order of Numeration;</hi> The hand muſt point at <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and <hi>newneſse of life,</hi> ere it ſtand at <hi>Deliverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But will you give me leave to follow <hi>Luther's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices</hi> to put this noment in the <hi>Predicament of relation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luther. in <hi>Pſal. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </note> and then he ſaith, it will Abſorbere praedicamentum quantitatis, <hi>quite ſwallow up the predicament of quantity:</hi> that is, compare the time of our ſufferings with that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our ſinnes, and the vaſteternity, which expects us hereafter, and you will confeſſe, 'tis not halfe a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt looke upon your ſinnes, on <hi>both ſides,</hi> Their <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Duration.</hi> The <hi>Guilt</hi> is <hi>eternall,</hi> though the <hi>Act</hi> be <hi>tranſient.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt in <hi>5. Joh.</hi> Caten. part. gr.</note> For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God judgeth not alwayes of ſinne by it's Continuance, but it's Nautre.</hi> Now, what proportion betweene a temporall puniſhment and an eternall one due? The very <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of an everlaſting fire,<note place="margin">Aug. Med.</note> made <hi>Auſtine</hi> cry out, Hie ure, hic feca modo in aeternum parcas, <hi>Burne me, O Lord, cut me in peices here, ſo thou would'st ſpare me for ever? O mercifull God,</hi> doe we murmur under a <hi>ſhort Purgatory</hi> in this life, when we are liable to an <hi>eternall torment?</hi> if every <hi>ſinne</hi> merit <hi>everlasting death,</hi> how <hi>many eternities of miſery</hi> are due to out
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113185:16"/>many crying ſinnes? yet thou haſt given us, but a <hi>Sip of ſorrow,</hi> that by a <hi>Praelibation</hi> of this <hi>bitter</hi> cup, we may prevent the drinking the <hi>very dregs</hi> in Hell: that by <hi>atast of tempor all miſery,</hi> we may never be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an <hi>eternali.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="2" place="margin">King. 17.5.</note> But will you as <hi>Elijah</hi> upon the Widowes Son, <hi>ſtretch this moment upon your ſinnes,</hi> lay mouth to mouth, and hands to hands, and what a <hi>vast diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> will you find, betweene this <hi>Little David,</hi> and that <hi>Huge Goliah?</hi> A Childe of foure yeares old, <hi>Our preſent ſorrowes,</hi> and this <hi>Philiſtin</hi> of threeſcore, <hi>Our paſt iniquities?</hi> The <hi>very fingar</hi> of this <hi>man of Gath, Our ſinnes,</hi> is bigger then the <hi>whole body</hi> of our ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, <hi>Job</hi> compares his ſinnes to the <hi>ſands of the Sea,</hi> and if you will ſit downe and tell the <hi>ſands of the Sea,</hi> and your <hi>ſufferings together,</hi> what <hi>Alpes,</hi> what <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of ſinne</hi> will you lay aſide for <hi>one little heape of ſorrow?</hi> O our <hi>Impanitency</hi> is our greateſt <hi>Calamity!</hi> This hath <hi>ſpun</hi> out the <hi>moment</hi> into ſo many <hi>yeares</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. For <hi>Warre</hi> is an <hi>Itinerary,</hi> not a <hi>manſionary</hi> evill: It is going it <hi>circuit</hi> through the World, and would ſoone paſſe through <hi>England,</hi> did not our many <hi>crimes</hi> deteine it in ſo <hi>long an Aſsize</hi> with us, Aske no more,<note place="margin">Jer. 4.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>How long ſhall I behold the Standard and heare the ſound of the Trumpet?</hi> When God doth ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine. <hi>My People are fooliſh, they have not knowne me: they are wiſe to doe evill, but to doe good they have no knowledge.</hi> Wonder not, that the deſire of our hearts, <hi>Peace,</hi> hath been ſo long an <hi>abomination</hi> to our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, when the <hi>Almighty</hi> doth yet <hi>ſtretch out his hands te Vs,</hi> a <hi>diſobedient</hi> and <hi>goine ſaying People.</hi> Lord, what
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113185:17"/>
               <hi>Vnreaſonable</hi> Creatures are we?<note place="margin">Salv. l. <hi>6.</hi> de gub. dei.</note> Volumus delinquere &amp; nolumus Verberari, <hi>We would of offend and not ſuffer for it.</hi> Thou muſt <hi>remove</hi> thy judgements, <hi>O God:</hi> but we may <hi>reteine</hi> our ſinnes: Thou muſt not <hi>afflict</hi> us, but we may <hi>diſhonour</hi> thee. I ſee I muſt be <hi>plaine</hi> with you: Is there a <hi>nasty drunkard, a rotten adulterer,</hi> or a <hi>damned ſwearer</hi> the leſſe for theſe ſad times? Are we not all more <hi>undone</hi> in our <hi>manners</hi> then our <hi>estates;</hi> and have we not <hi>leſse of virtue</hi> left us, then of our <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?</hi> Nay, would <hi>Salvian's</hi> complaint were not verified, Aſſiduitas calamitatum, augmentum crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, <hi>ô Incredible, The Continuance of our miſery doth but increaſe our iniquity,</hi> like that <hi>ſnaky monster,</hi> that <hi>multiplyed</hi> the more for the <hi>beheading?</hi> Boaſt not to me, what a <hi>good Subject</hi> thou art, when thou doſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit</hi> the King with thy <hi>mony,</hi> and <hi>rout</hi> him with thy <hi>ſinnes.</hi> Tell me not, what a <hi>freind</hi> thou art to thy <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country,</hi> when thou wilt not <hi>expend a luſt,</hi> to ſave it from ruine. How farre ſhort art thou of the very <hi>Heathens piety,</hi> who did not thinke the <hi>ſafety</hi> of their <hi>Nation</hi> too <hi>deare,</hi> at the price of their bloud, and yet thou wilt not part with <hi>one</hi> of thy <hi>ſinnes</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme it from deſtruction? Never ſpeake of <hi>peace</hi> more, ſo long as thou art thus at <hi>open Warre</hi> with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. If you would have God keep his <hi>moment in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing,</hi> why doe not you obſerve your <hi>modicum in ſinning.</hi> Can you blame the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> if the <hi>diſeaſe</hi> continues, when the <hi>Patient</hi> will not forbeare the <hi>meates that nouriſh it?</hi> An intemperate ſtomack doth but poyſon phyſick, and ſo feed the <hi>malady</hi> with the <hi>medicine.</hi> And will you thinke the <hi>Almighty cruell,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113185:17"/>That the Warre laſts, when <hi>Nos per noſtrum non patimur ſeelus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Our ſinnes</hi> will not ſuffer the <hi>Enraged Diety</hi> to put up his Sword. Alas! <hi>His mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> hath hitherto waited upon <hi>Ours:</hi> O <hi>Jeruſalem, wilt thou not be made cleane? when will it once be?</hi> For <hi>God's</hi> ſake, for the <hi>King's</hi> ſake, yea for <hi>Sion's</hi> ſake, <hi>let this be the day.</hi> God hath even put <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> in our owne power, and why will you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre your happineſſe any longer? <hi>Humble</hi> your Soules under the <hi>mighty hand of God,</hi> and he will bend the ſtubborne hearts of our Enemies to Peace. Doe but <hi>Repent</hi> of your ſinnes, and the <hi>Warre</hi> is <hi>ended:</hi> make your <hi>Peace with God,</hi> and goe, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime Peace,</hi> throughout all <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Once more;</hi> Compare the time of your ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering on Earth to that of your raigning in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and if a <hi>Thouſand yeares be but as a day in that Kingdome,</hi> we have not yet ſuffered the hundred thouſand'th minute of an houre of that day. The vaſt circumference of the Earth conteines more then <hi>two thouſand and five hundred miles,</hi> yet the <hi>Mathematician</hi> will prove 'tis but a <hi>Point</hi> in reſpect of the Heavens,<note place="margin">Kecher. Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph.</note> becauſe from any <hi>ſuperficies</hi> he doth not leſſe behold <hi>halfethe Heavens,</hi> then if he were in the Center of the Earth. So the many thouſand yeares extenſion of ſorrow, is butan <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> in reſpect of eternity: Becauſe eternity ſeems not leſſe eternall if you look upon it from the very <hi>Center of miſery.</hi> Will you ſee it tryed by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſtept up into the <hi>Third Heaven,</hi> to wrigh
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113185:18"/>
               <hi>the Croſse</hi> and <hi>the Crowne.</hi> And returned with this joyfull <hi>Probatum eſt,</hi> The <hi>most ponderous Croſse</hi> is but a feather in the ſcales,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> a <hi>Momentary light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse,</hi> in compariſon of that <hi>ſurpaſsing, exceeding, eternall,</hi> (where ſhall I ſtay?) <hi>weighty Crowne of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Complaine not then of <hi>thy ſhort paine,</hi> when an <hi>eternall eaſe</hi> expects thee. Thinke not that <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row long,</hi> that ends in <hi>everlasting joy:</hi> but hold out this little moment, thou haſt but this one ſtep to thy <hi>Crowne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</note> And as the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> when he was going to ſuffer, <hi>threw</hi> away his <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> and <hi>bid his legges doe their duty, He ſhould not trouble them farre.</hi> So command thy <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> to doe <hi>their last office,</hi> Jàm patùm itineris reſtat, <hi>Thou art almost at thy journyes end,</hi> at the very gates of Immortality: And what a <hi>diſhonour</hi> to faint at the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Race?</hi> what a <hi>misfortune,</hi> to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>ſhipwracke</hi> in the <hi>Haven?</hi> ſtretch thy patience, but a moment, and what a <hi>bleſſed Change</hi> wilt thou finde it, To <hi>breath</hi> thy Soule out of <hi>ſorrowes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>joy,</hi> out of <hi>miſery</hi> into <hi>happineſse,</hi> out of <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> into <hi>pleaſures for evermore.</hi> For our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent affliction, will but adde to the <hi>degrees</hi> of our Happineſſe, and we ſhall be the <hi>more bleſſed,</hi> that we were once <hi>ſo miſerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O deare Lorà, ſo inflame our hearts with the love of Aeternity, that the longeſt affliction may ſeeme ſhort, the heavieſt light, in compariſon of that everlaſting bliſse which thou hast prepared for us in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113185:18"/>thy Kingdome. Vnto which bring us, for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Jeſus, to whom with thee and the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be aſcribed all Honour and Glory, for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 7. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>r.</hi> Their bondage is His captivity. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>for</hi> would, <hi>r.</hi> could.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
